<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>generic test domain on generic test domain </title>
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://generictestdomain.net/index.xml</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 21:13:56 BST</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>A worked example of monitoring a queue based application</title>
      <link>http://generictestdomain.net/post/monitoring-queue/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 21:13:56 BST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://generictestdomain.net/post/monitoring-queue/</guid>
      <description>Stash Deferred At Qubit, we have a service named &amp;lsquo;Stash Deferred&amp;rsquo;. It reads from a database, GCP&amp;rsquo;s Cloud Bigtable, and writes to AWS&amp;rsquo;s Kinesis. Recently it underwent a bit of a renovation by the team that I am on, and a colleague commented that the end result had quite good monitoring, potentially worth of being a case study. Anyway, so here&amp;rsquo;s that.
Stash Deferred is a system for deferring message writes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The applications of Top Gun to software engineering</title>
      <link>http://generictestdomain.net/post/topgun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2017 21:35:50 BST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://generictestdomain.net/post/topgun/</guid>
      <description>The Merriam-Webster dictionary defines Top Gun as &amp;lsquo;a 1986 American romantic military action drama film directed by Tony Scott&amp;rsquo;. This definition might serve us well at the local pub quiz, but there is much more to learn about this film. During a recent viewing, I realised that there were a large number of useful parallels and not so parallels between the disciplines of piloting fighter aircraft in 80&amp;rsquo;s action films and developing robust software.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weave is kinda slow</title>
      <link>http://generictestdomain.net/post/weave-is-kinda-slow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 15:19:12 BST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://generictestdomain.net/post/weave-is-kinda-slow/</guid>
      <description>UPDATE: The Weave folk now say Weave is kinda fast: http://weave.works/weave-docker-networking-performance-fast-data-path/ In our new world of containers Docker, many old problems have been rediscovered. Thankfully, the fact that these problems were solved decades ago has not stopped people from coming up with their own solutions, and we now all get to witness the resulting disasters.
The particular problem I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about today is IP level overlay networks. The basic problem these overlay networks try to solve is &amp;ldquo;I have 1 IP per machine, but I need a subnet multiple IPs per machine&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

